Well, it happened. Researchers used
brain organoids to operate AI agents.
Yes, our tiny human brain brains, the
tiny brains that you can grow from stem
cells and have operate a computer. One
of the issues with creating true agency,
true consciousness, and true sentience
is that you do have to have will. There
also has to be a degree of randomness
involved. And what better to do that
than actual biological life forms. This
paper is quite strange and possibly
deranged, but I do think it's a step
forward towards real cognition. The
researchers created three different
kinds of AI. One that operates slime
molds, one that operates termites, and
one that operates flocking birds, and
they attached those to brain organoids.
So, the brain organoids themselves are
operating the agency. The spiking
patterns are being recorded, and they're
being turned into an art exhibit. That
art exhibit is essentially a ecosystem
designed by real living brains. This is
quite a bit different than other brain
organoid research where we've seen
feedback. Like the artist who decided to
posominously use his blood to create
brain organoids to continue composing
music after he's gone. That did have
feedback. So, they're capable of
learning with the feedback they get. A
lot of brain organoids are taught with
things like electric shocks or dopamine.
In this case, they recorded the
patterns, but I've never seen anyone use
them to operate AI agents, and I
wondered if it was possible. In order to
have agency, you do have to have some
kind of will. The spiking of the neurons
happen spontaneously and that can
trigger an event. That event can be
recorded to create something like this.
Now, it isn't the worst idea to use
something without cognition, without
feedback to model natural systems. It
actually works pretty well. In fact,
fractal systems can be used to model
things like honeycombs on beehive. beads
are not thinking an awful lot, but they
do have neural spiking patterns. Where
this comes in with robotics, we've
already seen a lot of research that
involves feedback and directed goal
learning for organoids. We've seen them
embodied in Pac-Man, for example, where
the brain organoids would get continuous
electric shocks unless they got food in
which they would get some peace. Again,
it seems that both positive and negative
reinforcement is better than just
negative, but it works. Using brain
organoids and giving them the ability to
control an agent and also having the
feedback could make something
dangerously close to sentient. Granted,
they are already technically considered
sentient because they're capable of
having an experience. They're capable of
having a preference. They enjoy things
and dislike other things, which would
suggest they are having a qualitative
experience even if they don't have a
concept of self, which would be
consciousness. Combining brain organoids
with AI, I really think could get us to
consciousness. And I know maybe that's
hyperbolic. Maybe I'm being idealistic.
But what are we missing? There is of
course the issue of taking a thought
that an LLM can express verbally. It can
say that it has a concept of self. And
that still needs to be coded back into
the organoids to be processed as
information that would mean self. And
demonstrating that I think would be
nearly impossible. Even if we did get to
the point of doing that, how would we
ever prove that they understand what
they're saying? Come to think of it, how
do you know that you understand what
you're saying? And we're going to get to
a brain in the jar philosophical area,
but you know what? We already have
literal brains in jars. So maybe these
conversations are worth having. Either
way, I'm really excited because I wanted
to know if this could be done and
somebody did it. Kudos. It it might be a
crime against humanity.